-Mom. -Yeah?
-媽媽 -嗯？
Am I not your daughter?
我不是你的女兒嗎？
Because,
因為
look at this. I'm Blood type AB.
你看這個，我是AB型
Mom, you're Type O, right?
你是O型吧？
Type O moms can't have Type AB children.
O型不會生出AB型
Mom,
媽媽
who are you?
你是誰？
Back then, I was only 23 or 24.
大約在我23或24歲的時候
I had someone I loved a lot.
遇到一個非常喜歡的人
I thought I was born in this world to meet him.
彷彿我就是為了與他相遇而生
He was my whole world.
他是我的全世界
But…
可是他卻背叛了我
Back then, Mom… Oh.
當時媽媽…
I was
我…非常依賴他
When I thought I lost him,
一想到我會失去他
I felt like I had lost the ground I was standing on.
就好像失去了腳下的地面
-You weren't a writer yet? -What?
-你當時還不是作家嗎？ -什麼？
If you were a writer,
若你當時已經成為作家
maybe writing would have
寫作這件事
saved Aoi Minase.
也許會幫忙拉水無瀨碧一把
It was the opposite.
正好相反
The Scent of the Sky became a huge hit quickly,
《聞見天空的氣味》莫名大紅
and the world put me on a pedestal.
獲得大眾的喜愛
They expected a lot from me,
大家寄予我的期待變成壓力
Living was only pain.
活著的一切變得很痛苦
I had nowhere to go.
令我走投無路
I felt like I had no reason to keep living.
我覺得自己沒有活下去的意義
I didn't feel like I had a purpose.
活著對我而言沒有意義
I think I was depressed.
可能有點憂鬱症吧
So…
於是
I went to the forest in Ashigaoka.
我到了蘆之丘的樹海
Now that I think about it, it was the first time
如今回想起來，那就像我漫長人生中
in my long life where I thought of that sort of thing. So, Mom…
迷失自我的短暫瞬間，媽媽…
I…
我…
I tried to die.
想要尋短
Going into the forest through the entrance,
我從樹海入口往深處前進
the leaves were so pretty.
樹葉很美
I wasn't scared of anything.
沒有任何恐懼
If I just kept on.
就這樣
-Kept walking on and on… -Mom!
-繼續向前走的話… -媽媽
I thought I could die.
我想一死了之
I kept going deeper into the forest.
當我愈來愈深入樹海
But then, I heard a voice.
卻聽到了聲音
The voice of a baby crying.
是嬰兒的哭聲
It was you.
你嚎啕大哭
You were…
你充滿生命力
You were placed in a tiny basket.
躺在小小的籃子裡
You had these tiny hands and a tiny face.
小小的手，小小的臉
And you were crying, with your face all red.
哭得滿臉通紅
I found myself
我
reaching out to you without realizing it.
不知不覺間伸出了手
I picked you up in my arms.
將你抱起來
And you were so warm.
你的身體好溫暖
So, so warm.
很溫暖…
I couldn't stop crying
我也不自覺地
at the fact that you were so warm.
因為你的溫暖而哭得唏哩嘩啦
My tears kept falling.
止不住眼淚
It woke me up.
彷彿瞬間清醒
I decided to keep living,
決定活下去
and to raise this child.
我決定養育這個孩子
That's a wild story.
好驚人的故事
Yeah, totally wild.
對啊，好驚人
But that means, the abandoned baby and…
這樣說起來 這代表被拋棄的孩子跟…
Oh, sorry.
對不起
No. It's the truth.
不會，這是事實
And Aoi Minase who was trying to die,
是孩子跟尋短的水無瀨碧
both their lives were saved, right?
拯救了彼此的生命？
I guess so.
是啊
I didn't know fateful meetings like that existed in real life.
原來世上真有命中注定的相遇
Isn't that more impressive than giving birth?
這比生小孩還厲害吧？
Yeah.
是啊
Then, when Mom picked me up,
我媽抱起我
she looked up for the first time that day
那天第一次抬頭仰望
and realized it was sunny.
發現那天是個大晴天
And she cried at how blue the sky was.
看到一片藍天的她，忍不住哭了出來
That's why she named me Sora, after the sky.
所以她才把我取名為小空
That's so moving. It makes me cry!
好感動，實在太感人了
Don't cry!
不要哭啦
After I heard that, I didn't care about blood types anymore,
聽完之後，我覺得管它什麼血型
or about blood relations.
有沒有血緣關係都無所謂了
Yeah.
嗯
Honestly, if me being abandoned saved Mom
我當時被拋棄在那裡
who was trying to die,
意外救了試圖尋短的媽媽
I feel glad that I was abandoned in the forest.
“還好我有被丟在樹海”
That's what I thought.
我甚至會這麼想
You're your Mom's life, Sora.
你是你媽媽的生命
What?
什麼？
Because you were here, your Mom decided to live,
是你給了你媽活下去的動力
and kept on living.
她才能走到現在
But you know, I don't really know what to do right now.
不過還是有點不知所措
Sora! You want some Milba?
小空，要吃牛奶紫羅蘭冰淇淋嗎？
Hazelnut and Clione!
榛果跟海天使口味
You can't eat Clione. It's Praline.
海天使不能吃，是焦糖杏仁
Oh, right! You're right.
對喔，是焦糖杏仁
It feels awkward just to laugh.
感覺連笑都很尷尬
Yeah, but you know,
不過親生家庭也是這樣啊
When you live with them versus
與家人同住時
after you move out,
開始自己住之後
your relationship with your family changes.
與家人的距離和氣氛都會改變
That's true. Nothing stays the same forever.
也是
It doesn't have to be the same forever.
就算不是永遠一樣也無所謂啊
As long as you want to be in each other's lives,
只要是真心想陪伴對方，就不會分離
even if it's imperfect.
就算是以奇怪的形式
You look upside down.
你顛倒過來了
An upside-down Hikaru.
顛倒的阿光
Why my first name?
怎麼突然叫我名字？
You call me Sora sometimes too. It's okay, right?
你不也叫我小空嗎？可以吧？
You don't have a single page of Midsummer Skies are Dreams written?
《仲夏藍天之夢》連一頁也沒寫？
Yes. Not one line, not one word.
是，一行也沒寫，一個字也沒寫
Well…
這…
-We have five pages for serialization. -Yes.
-我已經空下五頁的連載欄位了 -是
The book will be released around May next year…
也安排要在明年五月出版
Did something happen?
發生什麼事了嗎？
Yes. Something happened.
發生了
I may not be able to write for a while.
我短時間內可能無法動筆了
You say a while, but you haven't written forever…
不是短時間吧？您一直都沒在寫
My daughter's not my real kid.
我女兒不是我親生的
-What? -I'm not her real mother.
-什麼？ -其實我不是她的生母
And she found out.
這件事曝光了
Is it okay that you're sharing this with me?
您不介意告訴我嗎？
Konishi knows too. And Ms. Matsuyama.
小西也知道
They're so open-minded.
你好公開
I can trust Konishi in that regard.
這方面我可以信賴小西
Konishi doesn't say unnecessary things. He only does what benefits him.
只會做對自己有利的事，這就是小西
I don't mean to be intrusive, but,
不過恕我冒昧請問
how did you come to care for Sora?
您是何時，出於什麼原因收養她？
I found her in the forest.
我在樹海撿到她的
What? So your mom isn't your mom?
你媽媽不是你媽媽？
Yeah.
嗯
So cold!
好冰喔
I got confused and tried to make you laugh.
我太混亂了，所以先裝傻一下
But is it okay that you're sharing this with me?
這樣沒關係嗎？告訴我這麼私密的事
We became friends the other day.
我們從上次就變成朋友啦
I have toxic parents, so that wouldn't bother me,
因為我父母是毒親 所以我覺得這沒什麼
but you must be in shock.
但你打擊很大吧
A little.
有一點
Also, apparently,
而且
I was abandoned in the forest.
我好像被拋棄在樹海
-I don't think you were abandoned. -What?
-我覺得你不是被拋棄 -什麼？
I can totally imagine it in my mind.
我想像中的畫面是這樣
When your mom went to the forest,
你媽媽到森林裡
she found a beam of light.
看到一道亮光
And she found the cutest baby ever!
沒想到是個好可愛的嬰兒
-Like Princess Kaguya. -What?
-你是輝夜姬 -什麼？
You're just like Princess Kaguya, Sora!
因為你就像輝夜姬一樣
You're cute, you have black hair, and you're very Japanese.
很可愛，頭髮很黑，有和風美
-Very Japanese? -You look like you'd return to the moon.
-和風… -感覺隨時會回到月亮去
Sora.
小空
You weren't abandoned.
你不是被拋棄
You're an angel who fell from the sky.
你是從天而降的天使
And your mom was a very lucky girl for finding you!
而你媽媽很幸運地發現了你
Sally.
沙沙
What's up, Sora?
小空，你怎麼了？
You know… I…
我…
I only felt gratitude
我很感謝媽媽把我撿回來
but it bothered me
但對於自己被拋棄的事
that I was abandoned as a baby.
我心裡一直很在意
-Sora. -So…
-小空 -所以…
When you say it like that,
聽到你這麼說
it makes me feel much, much, better!
我覺得非常非常寬慰
Don't go back to the moon, Princess Kaguya.
輝夜姬，你不可以回月亮喔
Please stay here forever.
要一直留在這裡
UMBILICAL CORD - SEASON ONE
（《命之臍帶》）
CHIROPRACTOR: TAIYOU-DO
（太葉堂推拿院）
Have you been diving lately? Skydiving?
你最近還有去跳傘嗎？
-It's scuba diving. -Probably not. It's winter.
-是水肺潛水 -現在正值冬天啊
Scuba diving in winter is pretty nice too.
不過冬天潛水也很不錯喔
You must be busy with your dates?
是忙著約會嗎？
-Oh, not at all. -Not at all?
不
She doesn't call me at all.
我們都沒聯絡
We went on a date recently, but…
雖然上次有去約會
Is something wrong?
發生什麼事嗎？
She's a little cold.
她也不是冷淡
A little aloof, like she's distracted.
只是有點心不在焉
I wonder if something happened.
可能有什麼煩惱吧
But when I ask her about it on the phone, she says, "It's nothing."
但我問她怎麼了
But I'm sure something happened, so I ask her if
我想她肯定是遇到什麼困難
something happened at home, and she says, "It's nothing."
可是就算我問她是不是家裡有事 她也說沒有
-Maybe something at school… -Doctor, that's too annoying.
-說不定是在大學… -師傅，你太纏人了
Only ask "Did something happen?" once.
“發生什麼事了”只能問一次
If she doesn't answer, you have to let it go.
如果對方不回答，你就要放棄
No matter how hard it is, stories always save me.
無論何時，故事總能拯救我
I'm Mom's kid after all.
我果然是媽媽的女兒
Even if we're not related by blood,
就算沒有血緣關係
we're connected, somehow.
我們之間肯定也有某種連結
She's calling for ice cream?
冰淇淋的牌子
Is she a child?
又不是小孩子
MATERNITY HANDBOOK
（母子手冊）
SORA &amp; AOI, FAMILY
（小空&amp;小碧 母女）
Sora and Aoi.
小空和小碧
UMBILICAL CORD
（臍帶）
I think that is an umbilical cord.
那應該就是所謂的臍帶
I found it at home.
我在家裡找到的
Maybe it's your mom's.
會不會是你媽的臍帶啊？
This is just my intuition, but I think it's mine.
直覺告訴我，這是我的臍帶
If I was abandoned in the forest, why does she have my umbilical cord?
如果我被拋棄在樹海 怎麼會有臍帶？
Hey, have you read this?
你看過這本書嗎？
Mom's novel that got canceled.
媽媽被腰斬的小說
I only read manga.
我只看漫畫
I've never read Mom's novels.
從沒看過我媽的小說
There is a
這本書裡面
really similar scene in this book. Right here.
有一模一樣的情節，這段
"Nagisa held Ito in her arms and cried in the forest.
“小渚抱起小系，在樹海哭了出來
She looks up at the sky and sees how blue it is.
那時的天空一片蔚藍 她看著藍天放聲大哭
I'll raise her. If I don't raise her now, she will die.
‘我要養育這孩子 現在這孩子沒有我會死掉
That's how I found my reason to live. My reason to live, to raise this child."
而我也找到了活下去的意義 也就是活下去養育這孩子’”
You should put a little more emotion in that.
你要多放點感情啦，這是故事高潮耶
-It's a carbon copy. -Right?
-一模一樣 -對啊，很奇怪吧？
She doesn't care about selling her own life.
一點也不在乎出賣她的人生
She'd rather turn that into money to eat yakiniku at Hamada.
反而樂於以此換錢，去吃濱田燒肉
But that story,
但我覺得這件事
it sounds too perfect. It felt too beautiful to me.
實在太虛幻，太優美了
It's like a novel.
就像小說情節一樣
-If there's one thing… -What?
-要說哪裡怪的話… -什麼？
If there's one thing that bothers me about this whole thing…
其實在我內心深處 一直覺得有件事很奇怪
What is it?
是什麼啊？
Mom. That woman,
我媽，她那個人
Aoi Minase. I'm so sure that she wouldn't do it.
水無瀨碧 是絕對不可能會尋短的類型
Just like a cockroach, she'll live until she's killed.
就像蟑螂一樣
She's like a ball of life.
沒錯，她就是生命的化身
This is awful.
完全沒靈感
MIDSUMMER SKIES ARE DREAMS
（《仲夏藍天之夢》）
Aoi went to die in the forest,
小碧去樹海尋短
and found the abandoned Sora and took her in.
然後在那裡撿到小空
That's the very general explanation.
超簡略說明就是這樣
I have to go prep for dinner.
我差不多該去做傍晚的準備了
Kenta's working.
店裡有健太幫忙
You can't run away.
不可以逃跑
Why did Aoi say such a thing…?
小碧幹嘛這樣說啊？
So it's a lie! Mom told a lie!
果然是謊話，媽媽說謊了吧？
That bitch! I won't forgive her!
那傢伙，不可原諒！
Telling a lie in that moment?
誰會在那種情況下說謊！
Stay calm, Sora.
小空，冷靜
After I couldn't sleep the whole night because of our blood types…
我可是為了血型的事情
You were asleep! I couldn't sleep!
你根本睡死，沒睡的是我
-When did that happen? -No, it's not like that.
-你們何時… -沒發生什麼事
-Nothing happened at all! -Not a thing.
-沒發生任何事 -沒錯
I couldn't sleep
總之，我煩到睡不著
and I felt pain!
心情很痛苦
I tried to desperately
努力試著用自己的方式
accept the truth
接受真相
in my own way.
拼命說服自己接受
Am I not your daughter?
我不是你的女兒嗎？
What the hell is this?
她為什麼要這樣？好不容易…
I believed in her story and accepted it
相信媽媽說的話
and came to terms with it in my own way
接受真相，盡我所能去理解
and felt immense gratitude for her!
還覺得很感謝她
I thought that now,
以為我之後
I could keep being with Mom
能好好跟媽媽相處
and stay by her side…
能繼續跟她一起生活
Sora. It's because of this crummy old thing!
小空，千錯萬錯都是這個東西的錯
What! He ate it!
什麼？吃掉了！
What are you doing, Dad!
老爸，你在幹嘛？
You wanna make Suzu cry?
鈴小姐會哭的！
"Suzu"?
鈴小姐？
It's a magic trick. It looks like I swallowed it, right?
只是類似魔術的手法 很像真的吞下去吧？
You really surprised us!
我快嚇死了
-Here. -Okay!
-來 -好
-We're leaving, Kenta. -Yes, sir.
-健太 -是
-Here you are. -Thanks.
-好的 -謝啦
-Safe travels!
-路上小心 -好
-I can come too? -If you can.
-我也可以去嗎？ -你願意的話
Sora, I'm sorry about this.
小空，這還給你，抱歉啦
You should've swallowed it.
還不如讓你真的吞掉呢
If you say that, Shunichiro will really eat it!
小空你這麼說，他真的會吃掉喔
He really cares about you, Sora.
因為俊一郎超疼你的
I'm sorry for causing this much concern.
讓大家擔心了，非常抱歉
It's really nothing.
沒這回事
Sally.
沙沙
I'll go to your place with Shunichiro.
我也要跟俊一郎去小空家
What? It sounds like
你們只是想知道事情的後續發展吧？
I'M SORRY, I CAN'T WRITE.
（對不起 我寫不出來…）
Sorry. I can't write at all.
對不起，我完全寫不出來
I took the plot summary you gave me
總之，我之前按照大綱
and divided it into four sequences.
分成了四大段 希望能讓您比較好下筆
-This is really helpful. -How is it?
-太感謝了 -怎麼樣？
But these things hold back free associations!
這種東西會限制我的自由發想
My unpredictable imagination would die!
我充滿創意的想像力會凋零！
Sorry. I'm kidding.
對不起，我說笑的
I just wanted to talk like an artist, just this once.
我只是想說說看這種藝術家會說的話
I'll look through this.
我會拿來參考
Hello.
你好
-Come in, come on in. -Okay.
-請，別客氣 -好
-Thank you. -Please take a seat.
-打擾了 -大家隨便坐
Shunichiro and Sally, sit here.
俊一郎跟沙沙坐這裡
What about Gon-chan?
阿欣怎麼辦？
Gon-chan, sit here. And Hikaru…
阿欣坐這好了，光…
Are you Soseki?
你就是漱石嗎？
-How could you tell? -It's obvious! There's hair in his eyes.
-你怎麼知道？ -那當然
He's tall and sharp, and his legs are thin!
身材很瘦，下半身很精實
I'm really sorry about what happened.
實在非常抱歉
-It's not something to apologize about… -Wait a second, you guys!
-你不需要道歉 -慢著…等一下
Today's not the day for this! We're not all here today
這不是今天的重點 大家來這裡不是要講這個
during Odaya's peak hours,
在小田屋正要開始忙的此時
leaving Kenta to do everything to do this!
把工作交給健太跑來這裡 並不是為了這件事
Wow, you've become quite the leader.
你好像指揮官
Huh? What the heck is up with that attitude?
怎麼了？
I'll make some tea.
我去泡茶吧
Right, tea! Since everyone's here.
對喔，泡茶，這裡這麼多人
-I brought taiyaki and sanmayaki too. -Good idea.
-我帶了一些鯛魚燒 -也有秋刀魚燒喔
I'll help serve.
我來幫忙裝盤吧
Don't run away!
不准開溜！
I'm not here to have
我不是要在這裡開下午茶會
I brought everyone here
我找大家來
because Mom lies when it's just us two.
是因為我媽對我撒了謊
I brought the Odaya members because they know my past.
兩位似乎知曉詳情的小田屋成員
Mom.
媽媽
UMBILICAL CORD
（臍帶）
This is an umbilical cord.
這是臍帶吧？
Just like your novel.
是《命之臍帶》吧？
Why did you lie to me and say you found me in the forest?
為什麼要撒謊說是在樹海撿到我的？
Tell me the truth.
你跟我說實話
I prepare it like so
像這樣
and sell these.
把這個拿去賣
I see.
是喔
-Do you dive in the winter often? -Yes.
-你冬天也會來潛水啊？ -是的
The sea bream are beautiful.
金海鯽很漂亮
Also, I want to feel refreshed.
另外也算是轉換心情
-Refreshed? -Yes.
-轉換心情？ -是的
I'm about to get dumped.
我好像快被女生甩了
It's nice to be young.
年輕就是好啊
Excuse me.
不好意思
I take a photo of the sky.
我想在太陽下山前
-Before the sun sets. -I see.
-拍一張天空的照片 -這樣啊
-The sky is beautiful and calm today. -Yes.
-今天的天空很平靜，很漂亮 -是啊
The sky changes every day.
天空每天都會變化
It's never the same.
沒有一天是相同的
It's just like
就如同
our hearts.
我們人心一樣
I fell in love.
我談了一場戀愛
It wasn't like the love I'd experienced in the past.
跟以往的戀情截然不同
It was like I got struck by lightning. An overwhelming love.
彷彿受到雷擊一般，撼動心弦的戀愛
I think I'll get us some tea, actually.
我還是去泡個茶吧
Oh, me too! And how about you, Watt?
我也來幫忙，瓦特呢？
I want to hear this. Aoi Minase's one true love.
我想聽水無瀨碧的真實戀愛故事
Yes, yes. Love like you got struck by lightning!
嗯，彷彿受到雷擊般的戀愛
For a week after meeting him,
從認識他後整整一週
we never left each other's side.
我們形影不離
Sorry, I have final proofs due today so I'll be leaving.
對不起，我今天要末校
Why?
為什麼…
-Is something going on? -Excuse me, everyone.
-你對她有意思嗎？ -各位
I'm sure you have many feelings going on right now,
我知道大家心情很紊亂
but for now, for today,
但今天請團結一心
will you prioritize my feelings first?
以尊重我的心情為第一要務
I want to hear from Mom.
我想知道媽媽
The woman who raised me.
這個人，這位養育我長大的她
I want to hear how I met her,
是如何遇見了我
and how I came to be mother and daughter with her.
又是因什麼過去 才與我成為母女，我想知道
I…
我…
I loved him a lot.
很喜歡那個人
I think I still love him.
或許現在仍喜歡著他
No matter how many times I fell in love after that,
不管談幾次戀愛，總覺得
no one would be better than him.
似乎都無法超越對他的感情
I can't forget him.
無法忘記他
-A person you can't forget? -Yes.
-無法忘懷的人？ -是的
Originally,
對方是我小學三年級的同學
from third grade.
但我忘不了她
So strange, right?
很好笑吧？
No, I get it.
不會，我能體會
I have someone I can't forget either.
我也有忘不了的人
Someone who grows more vibrant
日子愈過愈久
in my memories as more time passes.
記憶的輪廓反而變得愈深
-His name is Fuga Ichinose. -A stage name?
-他叫一之瀨風雅 -是藝名嗎？
These are his photos.
這是他的照片
No way! He's so handsome!
我的天啊，媽，他超帥的
It's a bromide.
是拍立得
A bromide?
還說什麼拍立得 現在都什麼年代了？
No, they still say that. They sell three photos for 600 yen.
現在也是叫拍立得，三張600圓
-I paid 1,000 yen. Was I ripped off? -Is this from Ofuse?
這個三張要1000呢 我被坑了嗎？
It was a theater near Shimokitazawa Station.
下北澤的驛近劇場
I attended his performance many times.
我去看了好幾場他的演出
Life is but a walking shadow!
人生不過是行走的黑影
Tears are the smallest seas
眼淚是人所能創造面積最小的海洋
Only three in the audience today?
搞什麼？只有三個客人啊？
-Let's quit this show. -No, don't stop!
-今天不演了 -等一下，不要取消
I'm watching.
有我在看啊
That was how we met.
那就是我們的邂逅
Does that count as meeting him? That's like an idol otaku
那算邂逅嗎？ 這就跟以為本命在看自己
saying, "He looked at me!"
好像有對上眼神 就興奮不已的阿宅一樣吧
No. We met that day.
不是，的確是邂逅
Then, we fell in love.
我們就這樣墜入愛河
And after a week he went.
過了一星期左右
-He disappeared. -What?
-他就消失了 -什麼？
He probably used you.
他這是玩弄你的感情吧
I went to his theater troupe
我跑去他的劇團
and figured out where he lived.
問到他的住處
What?
什麼？
I'm sorry. Ichinose's not here right now.
對不起，一之瀨不在這裡
He left six months ago.
他半年前就離開了
I'm sorry.
對不起
Wait a minute. You look pale!
等一下，你臉色很差
Are you pregnant?
孕婦？
Do you have a baby?
你懷孕了
That's Suzu?
她就是鈴小姐嗎？
Yes.
對
She's your mother.
她是你的母親
-She was born with a weak heart. -Suzu?
-鈴小姐本來就有心臟病 -鈴小姐？
She was trying to have the baby against doctors' orders.
但還是堅持要生下你
She really wanted to have you.
她無論如何都想生下你
What the hell are you thinking?
你到底在幹嘛？
It's the ex-girlfriend of the guy you like, right?
她是你心儀對象的女友吧？
Why are you taking care of her?
你幹嘛要照顧她？
She has no family. Well, she does, but she can't depend on them.
她沒有什麼家人啊 有是有啦，但都不可靠
How does that lead to you visiting her in the hospital?
就算是這樣，你幹嘛每天跑醫院？
I can't leave someone alone if they need help.
看到有困難的人 總不忍心視而不見啊
ODAYA
（小田屋）
Wow, it's good.
好好吃
Don't eat too fast.
別勉強自己喔
If Ichinose left
既然一之瀨先生
six months ago, does that mean he doesn't know
他在半年前就離開了
you're pregnant?
也就是說他不知道你懷孕的事嗎？
He doesn't.
不知道
This is a bit awkward for me to say,
這麼說有點對不起你
but a lot of women other than you
不過除了你以外 還有很多女人去公寓找他
I was an actress, you know?
我本來是個女演員
In the same theater troupe as Ichinose.
跟一之瀨隸屬同一個劇團
You're really beautiful. That's what I guessed.
我看你長得這麼漂亮，多少有猜到
But I couldn't fight that hard for my career.
但是我無法全力以赴
I wasn't that type of girl.
我不是個積極努力的人
I'm not ambitious.
也沒什麼野心
I just wanted to be with the man I love.
我只想跟心愛的男人在一起
That's all.
僅此而已
That's all there is to me.
我只不過是這樣的女人
I think it's straightforward and admirable.
我覺得這樣很單純，很帥氣
I want to meet Ichinose's child.
我想生下一之瀨的孩子
He's a butthead,
雖然他是個爛男人
but I love him, so I want to have this kid no matter what.
但我還是愛他，想生下他的孩子
But I wasn't thinking about this child at all.
可我完全沒考慮到這孩子
I…
我…
I might die.
可能會死
If that happens,
那麼這孩子…
what'll happen to this child?
這孩子該怎麼辦？
-It's okay! Leave it to me! -What?
-放心，包在我身上 -什麼？
If something happens to you, Suzu,
如果你有什麼萬一
then I'll raise your child!
我會幫你養育孩子
So have this child!
所以你放心生產吧
Are you serious, Aoi?
小碧小姐，你是認真的嗎？
I'm serious.
是認真的
Why… Why would you do this much for me?
為什麼？ 你為什麼要幫我到這種程度？
We suffered at the hands of the same butthead.
誰叫我們遇到同一個爛男人
We're on the same team.
同是天涯淪落人
You remember how
你也讓我摸過肚子好幾次啊
Touch it.
你摸摸
I can feel her move.
這孩子在動呢
She's alive.
她擁有生命
This kid will be born to be happy.
這孩子是為了擁有幸福人生而降臨的
This kid will be born in this world to be happy!
是為了擁有幸福才來到這個世上
I will help to make that happen.
所以我會助她一臂之力的
On a beautiful sunny day,
在一個晴朗的日子
Suzu gave birth to Sora,
鈴小姐生下你
and after a while,
過了不久
she passed away.
就過世了
-She's a selfish woman! -What?
-真是自私的女人 -什麼？
She loved without a plan.
自己愛上那個男人
She gave birth without a plan.
不顧後果生下孩子，把小孩…
And she pushed her kid onto you, a total stranger! What the hell?
把小孩塞給身為外人的媽媽
She's insane! Just a stupid woman who went crazy from love!
那個女人根本有病 根本是為了愛發瘋的女人
Sora! Don't say those things!
小空，你說這什麼話？
Because it's so irresponsible!
誰叫她這麼不負責任！
I would've preferred to have been abandoned in the forest!
我還不如被人丟在樹海
She risked her life to have you! Don't you say that!
她賭上性命生下你 你怎能說這種話？
Apologize to Suzu!
給我向鈴小姐道歉！
Is this world
這個世界
so harsh on you? Are you in pain?
對你很嚴苛嗎？讓你很痛苦嗎？
Is this world not worth living for?
活在這世上沒有價值嗎？
Don't you know how much Suzu suffered to have you?
你知道鈴小姐 是用什麼心情生下你嗎？
I didn't ask for that!
我又沒拜託她！
Why does this have to be the reason
為什麼？
Why did you hit me?
為什麼要打我？
-Why! -Sora. It's okay.
-為什麼？ -小空…
-I'm right here.
-為什麼？ -我在這裡
Sora, calm down, okay?
小空，你冷靜一下
-Do you want water? -It's gonna be alright.
水，要不要喝水？
I'm taking Sora to Odaya.
我帶小空回小田屋吧
Why did you lie about finding her in the forest?
為什麼要謊稱在樹海撿到她？
Because you knew this would happen?
你早知道事情會變成這樣嗎？
I didn't want to tell her the truth.
我不想說實話
Because,
因為
Suzu passed away,
鈴小姐雖然不在了
but Sora's father is probably still alive.
但小空的父親應該還活著
She's related to that man by blood.
畢竟是血脈相連的父親
She might leave me for her father.
我怕她會去找爸爸
He might take Sora away.
我怕小空會被搶走
Are bloodlines that important?
血緣關係真有如此強烈嗎？
I'll never know.
我不知道
I never had a child.
我又沒有生過小孩
Should I call for Gon?
我叫阿欣先生來吧
Huh? What? Why?
為什麼？
Because he knows you the best
他是最了解你的人
and he's the person you want to be with the most right now.
我想你現在 應該最希望他能陪在你身邊吧
Soseki.
漱石
I'm sorry.
對不起
What are you apologizing for, exactly?
這句道歉是為了什麼？
Is it because I'm not the one you want and need now?
是為了你需要的人不是我
Is that it?
而向我道歉嗎？
I'm sorry. I don't want to fight you.
對不起，我太無理取鬧了
ODAYA
（小田屋）
Sora.
小空
Shunichiro and Gon-chan made us sweet bean soup.
俊一郎跟阿欣煮了紅豆湯喔
Thank you for the meal.
我開動了
It's so good!
真好喝
It's good.
好好喝
What's wrong?
你怎麼了？
I'm afraid Sora will break.
我很怕小空會崩潰
She won't break. She's not that weak.
不會啦，她沒那麼軟弱
I shouldn't be crying.
我都幾歲了
I'm an adult. So pathetic.
居然還哭成這樣，真沒用
It's fine.
沒關係啦
You're still 20, right? Life is long.
你才20歲，人生正要開始呢
Pretend you're a kid and cry. But…
就當自己還是孩子大哭一場吧，不過
Don't cry in front of Sora.
別在小空面前哭喔
Of course. I'm prepared to do that.
我知道
It's a promise between men. I'll keep it a secret.
這是男人間的秘密，我不會說出去的
-Want a drink? -Yes, sir.
-要喝酒嗎？ -好
I think Suzu,
鈴小姐
your birth mother,
你的生母
loved you very much Sora,
一定非常愛你
when you were in her belly.
從懷孕時就愛著你
You know how I told you
我是從津輕
I was pregnant back then.
當時我懷孕了
What?
什麼？
It's embarrassing, so I'm going to use my Tsugaru accent.
太羞於啟齒了 所以讓我用津輕腔說吧
Can you understand?
你聽得懂嗎？
Yeah.
聽得懂
And the father
可是
of that kid
那個男人不想當爸爸
didn't want to take any responsibility.
也一點都不想負責
I couldn't have it alone.
我一個人沒辦法養
I thought my life would end.
那樣我人生就完蛋了
So I got an abortion.
所以我就把孩子拿掉了
I really respect Suzu
努力生下你的鈴小姐
for having you, Sora.
我非常佩服她
She was brave. She had love.
她很有勇氣，很愛你
You came into this world through so much love.
生下你的人如此愛你
You were raised in this world with so much love.
養育你的人也如此愛你
What are you unhappy about?
你還有什麼不滿呢？
I… I…
我…因為我
I love Mom.
還是很愛媽媽
I love the mother I have now.
我愛現在的媽媽
So I…
我…
I wanted to be Mom's daughter!
我想要當媽媽的女兒！
What are you doing?
你在幹嘛？
I got what I wanted.
我錄到剛才那句了
I have proof right here.
這是證據
Your confession of love!
愛的告白
Hey, you…
你真是的
SORA'S CRY OF LOVE!
（小空的吶喊）
I… I…
我…
I wanted to be Mom's daughter!
我想要當媽媽的女兒！
Suzu. You did so well!
鈴小姐，辛苦你了
She's so energetic!
好有精神的女孩
Thank you.
謝謝你
I have to think of a name.
該替她想名字了
Oh, it's morning.
已經早上了
-I'll open the curtain. -Okay.
-我把窗簾拉開吧 -嗯
-Sora. -Sora… What?
-小空
"Sora" is a good name, right?
小空這個名字不錯吧？
I thought so too.
我也有同感
And the blue sky continues to this day
後來晴朗的藍天依舊
and I'm alive.
我仍然繼續過日子
Even after all this,
即便發生這樣的事
there's 24 hours in a day,
每天依舊是24小時
and the third period of Friday is the Keynes Seminar.
週五第三堂課依然是凱因斯專題討論
And the days just go on.
日子一如往常地過
The world is strong.
世界堅不可摧
It doesn't care about me.
完全不顧我的感受
-Awesome, yeah! -Sounds cool, doesn't it?
-太棒了 -很棒吧？
-A music festival? -Yeah!
-是音樂祭吧？一起去嗨爆 -好啊
-Definitely! -Perfect.
-當然好 -太棒了
Who do you want?
你在找誰？
I just saw you scan the room for someone.
你剛才像這樣在找誰吧？
A crow.
烏鴉
I was looking to see if there was a crow.
我在看教室有沒有烏鴉
It's Hikaru, right?
你在找阿光吧？
You've been hogging Hikaru lately. What do you want?
你最近都在獨佔阿光，是什麼意思？
I'm not hogging him.
我又沒獨佔他
He's not anyone's thing. He's a free man.
他不屬於任何人，他就是他
You're just a gloomy otaku!
你這陰沉的臭宅女
You think you're better than that?
囂張個屁啊？
-Stop it! So annoying! -Annoying? What the hell?
-夠了沒？煩死了 -你說誰煩？
Your perfume freaking stinks!
-你的香水臭死了！ -你找死！
-You bitch! -Hey, stop it! What's going on?
-好了啦，你在幹嘛？ -你這傢伙！
You too, Minase!
水無瀨同學也住手
-Hey! -You're annoying!
-喂…怎麼了？ -煩死了！
-What's going on? -Hikaru, help!
-光，幫幫忙 -幹什麼？你們在幹嘛啊？
For the first time ever,
我人生第一次
I got in a fight with a party girl.
跟陽光系派對女打了一架
-Why'd this happen? -No idea!
-怎麼會這樣？ -不知道
-Ouch! -Oh, sorry.
-好痛 -抱歉…
You don't need to be with Airi?
你不用去看看愛梨嗎？
-No. -Oh.
-不用啦 -為什麼？
Isn't she your current girlfriend?
她不是你現在的女友嗎？
I want a hotter girl, like a model.
我喜歡更像模特兒的類型
A girl with really high hips.
很高腰的那種
You like girls with nice figures.
你是身材協會的吧
What's her name?
你女友叫什麼名字？
It's Kokoro.
她叫心
That's a nice name.
名字很好聽
Sorry for all the trouble I've caused.
這次給大家添麻煩了
Aoi, it's not sweet bean soup today.
小碧，今天不是紅豆湯
We made zenzai. Your favorite, right?
是善哉喔，你喜歡吃善哉吧？
We got some really nice red beans from Tokachi by chance!
我碰巧拿到很好的十勝紅豆
I'm sorry. I'm only having tea today.
對不起，我今天喝茶就好
What? You don't have an appetite?
咦？小碧你沒食慾嗎？
-I'm sorry. -The ogre has weakened.
-對不起 -鬼也會生病啊
You must be worried about Sora.
你擔心小空吧
-How is she doing? -Well.
-後來你們怎麼樣了？ -是
It's been okay.
勉強還可以
-I'm home. -Welcome home.
-我回來了 -歡迎回家
I see.
這樣啊
I guess time will solve everything.
只能交給時間解決了
What?
什麼？
SAKURAHAMA PARK
（橫濱公園）
You've never rented it?
什麼？你沒租過車啊？
Don't be spoiled! I'm trying to ride the bike with you.
別鬧脾氣啦，我好心陪你騎腳踏車耶
Sorry, that came off strong. You weren't being spoiled.
我剛才失言了，你沒有鬧脾氣啦
I'm the one that said I'd join you…
是我自己要…
It's unlocked.
打開了
When you move your body,
動動身體
all your heavy parts fly away bit by bit
身上的沉重感似乎一點一滴
with the wind.
隨風消逝
The scenery keeps changing
景色緩慢的變化
and the truth falls and settles inside,
真相也慢慢沉澱
into my stomach.
沉澱到我內心深處
You don't need to rush.
你不必著急
-Don't force yourself. -Yeah.
-別勉強自己 -喔
But you know, your mom, every day,
但你媽媽日復一日
365 days for 20 years,
365天乘20年
carried those feelings
每一天都抱持著這種心情
while raising you,
將你養育成人
That's stronger than blood.
這比血脈重要多了吧
-Also. -Yeah?
-話說 -嗯？
Your mom decided to raise you at 23, right?
你媽媽決定養育你時是23歲吧？
We're 20 now.
我們現在是20歲
It's three years from now. That's so soon!
只差三年而已，真厲害
Would a normal person be prepared for that?
一般人可沒這個膽量
She's so cool.
真佩服她
She's determined and resolved.
好堅強的覺悟與決心
-Oh! -Hey, heads up!
-喔 -喂…看前面…
You okay?
你沒事吧？
-I'm fine. -Yeah?
-我沒事 -是喔
Yes?
請進
-It's me. -Hey, welcome home.
-小空 -歡迎回家
I got us Milba.
我買牛奶紫羅蘭回來了
The new flavor, Violet Apple.
新商品，紫羅蘭蘋果口味
Strange!
好詭異
Milba has some weird flavors sometimes. They're floundering.
他們有時出的口味好詭異 是撞牆期吧
I brushed my teeth already. I'll have it tomorrow.
我已經刷好牙了 幫我冰起來，我明天吃
What were you doing?
你在幹嘛？
Breaststrokes. I need exercise.
最近運動量不足，在練蛙式
Swim at the pool!
游泳要去泳池啦
You can drown in the pool.
去泳池會溺死啦
I drowned, and got a D in PE.
不會游泳的體育成績都很差
Just kidding.
說笑的
Yeah?
請進
Mom.
媽媽
Thank you.
謝謝你
Thank you for everything.
謝謝你養育我長大
What? Wait.
什麼？等一下，是誰？
Doctor Wataru? Are you getting married!
還是涉師傅要結婚嗎？
Isn't that too early? Maybe you should wait until graduation.
未免太早了，先等大學畢業吧
This is like "Cosmos," right?
這是在上演秋櫻情節嗎？
-Momoe Yamaguchi's pink "Cosmos." -What are you saying?
山口百惠那首《淺紅色秋櫻》
-A child, are you having a child? -Mom.
-孩子？有孩子了嗎？ -媽媽，你冷靜點
It's a long path to grandchildren.
未來還很長，你抱孫的日子還遠得很
And, we live in a prime location in Tokyo.
而且這裡是市中心高級地段
This house is a keeper. I'll keep relying on you.
不能捨棄這個家，我還要繼續啃老呢
I see. So why are you thanking me?
是嗎？那為什麼要道謝？
Thank you for
你一直養育我到現在
raising me until now.
謝謝你
I'm so grateful.
我很感謝你
No way!
別這樣
I want to keep raising you!
我還要繼續養你呢
No. It's not about that.
不，不是這個意思
You raised me,
我明明不是你的親生女兒
even though I'm not your daughter.
你還願意養育我
I finally know how I feel.
我終於整理好自己的心情了
Maybe I made myself understand.
雖然可以說是出於無奈
But I felt I needed to thank you.
但我覺得應該向你道謝
Sora.
小空
-You want to see a picture of Suzu? -What?
-你想不想看鈴小姐的照片？ -什麼？
-She's pretty. -She looks like you.
-她好漂亮 -你們很像
You think?
真的嗎？
After Suzu passed away,
自從她過世後
I…
我自己
I couldn't make breastmilk,
沒有辦法親餵母乳
so I could only bottle feed you.
只能用奶瓶餵
But you hated
可是
the smell of rubber.
你很討厭橡膠的味道
You wouldn't drink formula.
總是不喝奶
I thought that you would die!
我很怕你會死掉
I was so, so worried
很擔心
that you wouldn't grow up.
沒辦法好好養育你，內心非常不安
Mom.
媽媽
Mom, don't cry.
媽媽，你不要哭
I grew up.
小空長大了
Look how big she is!
已經長這麼大了
Sora is alive.
小空還活著
Mom.
媽媽
I thanked you,
我剛才向你道謝了
but I want to thank
我也想向鈴小姐道謝
She gave me life.
謝謝她生下我
Sora.
小空
I wish she could meet me.
想讓她看看我
Sora, I wanted to
我一直很想帶你過來
I'm so glad.
太好了
But, the guy who left Suzu.
不過那個拋棄鈴小姐
-That also abandoned you. -What?
-拋棄媽媽 -什麼？
This Ichinose guy who disappeared.
音訊全無的男人 一之瀨某某到底是什麼人？
What kind of guy is he?!
他到底是什麼傢伙？
I want to punch him in the face!
我想要痛揍他一拳
Mom!
媽媽
Where is this Ichinose asshole?
一之瀨某某人在哪裡？
I'll beat him up!
我要去揍扁他！
The sky is
今天的天空也很美
-We're going to see him. -We found him. We're going.
-我們決定去見他 -既然都找到了，當然要去
I won't give up on Sora.
我不會放棄小空的
-Romance is about two people, right? -Do you love her?
-戀愛是兩個人的事 -你現在還喜歡著小碧老師嗎？
-Is this your first time fishing? -Yes!
-你是第一次釣魚嗎？ -是
I looked for you!
我一直在找你